<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A comfortable and heauenly inquisition not made by the vnmercifull Pope, Christs pretended vicar: but by our mercifull God, in Christ, our assured louing father. Or a sermon preached at the funeralls of the vertuous and religious gentlewoman Mris. Neale of Homersfield in Suffolke.</title>
            <author>Day, Valentine, b. 1589 or 90.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19995</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852716</idno>
  <idno type="VID">18056</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240892093</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 6434</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S117503</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99852716e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19995)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18056)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1233:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A comfortable and heauenly inquisition not made by the vnmercifull Pope, Christs pretended vicar: but by our mercifull God, in Christ, our assured louing father. Or a sermon preached at the funeralls of the vertuous and religious gentlewoman Mris. Neale of Homersfield in Suffolke.</title>
                  <author>Day, Valentine, b. 1589 or 90.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 70 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by E. Griffin] for Nathaniel Butter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Valentine Day.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Gods inquisition after man.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17thcentury.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18056:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18056:1"/>
            <p>A COMFORTABLE AND HEAVENLY INQVISITION: Not made by the vnmercifull Pope, Christs pretended Vicar: but <hi>by our mercifull God, in Christ,</hi> our assured louing father.</p>
            <p>Or a Sermon preached at the <hi>Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralls of the vertuous and</hi> religious Gentlewoman M<seg rend="sup">ris</seg>. NEALE of Homersfield in <hi>Suffolke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for NATHANIEL BVTTER. 1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18056:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18056:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE SIR <hi>Edward Coke Knight, one of his</hi> Maiesties Honourable priuy Councellors <hi>Grace, Mercy, and Peace.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable,</hi> this sermon being prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at the funerall of your louing, and religious Sister M<seg rend="sup">ris.</seg>
               <hi>Neale,</hi> hath beene to me (as most children are to their parents) Both cause
<pb facs="tcp:18056:3"/>of griefe, and cost: but in what manner I think not fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to publish, let the world imagine it was by the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full blasts of malediction, &amp; enmity: for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, euill words wound deeper then sharpe swords, &amp; are the cause of much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention: &amp; albeit I can looke for no other but that <hi>perget maledicere, qui nunquam bene loqui didicit;</hi> he will not cease to speake euill who neuer learnt too speake well: yet in the midst of these blustring fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries this is my comfort that many wise and learned fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb facs="tcp:18056:3"/>(out of whose wels I haue drawne much for the furnishing of this little worke) haue in time past beene as little beholding to such as now I am; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore at length I haue learnt this wisdome that <hi>vituperari ab illaudato viro laudari est,</hi> it is the greatest praise to be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praysed of an vnworthy man: so that the sole care I now take for my wandring orphane, is that he may by his trauell atteine that fauour to be receiued to your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours seruice, and I shall then assure my selfe that <hi>nec oleum,
<pb facs="tcp:18056:4"/>nec operā perdidi,</hi> praying from my heart that he may do your honour that good ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice his place requires, to which end I cease not to pray to the Lord God that hee would preserue your honour vnblameable in your soule, and body vntill the day of his appearing.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your honours humbly<lb/> at command,</hi>
                  <lb/> VALENTINE DAY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18056:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>GEN. 3.9.</hi>
                  </bibl> Where art thou?</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O speake of all Gods benefits bestowed on our first parents, were to make too large a portall for this so small a building, it shall suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice therefore only to poynt out this one thing: that notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Gods manifold benefits, they sinned against God, and added this to their sinne that they fled from him, and God added this to his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer mercy, that he made this inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition after them, for he that kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth <hi>Israell</hi> neither slumbreth nor sleepeth; his eye and his care was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18056:5"/>them in their profoundest sleep: Adam may flie into the land of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulnesse, fall into the depth of dispaire, tyre himselfe in the wayes of wickednesse, as a man without strength, become free amongst the dead and exild from the law of the liuing: (for this was his estate) yet doth not God forsake him, but fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth after him drawing him to repentance, to make him an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of mercy to many babes yet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne. Of Iudgement therefore &amp; mercy is our song; Iudgement in his flight, mercy in his retraight, Iudgement in his hiding of sinne, mercy in Gods vncouering of it; for man was falen into a sleepe (not that sweete sleepe of the body whereby hee is refreshed, but that of the soule) in sinne, which makes me quake to thinke of, and that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so of soule, and body in eternall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18056:5"/>(which you cannot but tremble to heare of) had not God in mercy awaked him. O the height and depth of Gods mercy, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he suffereth his children to fall, yet not to lie and die in sinne, as the wicked world doth: but sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly striketh their harts with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance not to be repented of, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they be cauterised through cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome; as we see in a cloude of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses, as Dauid who when he had numbred the people his hart <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently smote him, and in Ionas who when hee was fled from God, the windes sent as a pursiuant to fetch him back, who else would haue posted to hel,</hi> for he was well onward in his iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hauing run to the hauen, paid his fare, entred the ship and slept securely in his sinne. Peter likewise thrust himselfe into euill company, <hi>for feare of a weake Damsell not only
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18056:6"/>denied, but with bitternesse forswore his master: but the crowing of the cock and the glance of his masters eye made him goe out and weepe bitterly.</hi> And <hi>Adam</hi> likewise receiued no lesse grace, for he had liked, lusted after, tasted the forbidden fruit, done his endeauour to couer himselfe with figg leaues, and his sinne with a sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and slender excuse: but God leaues him not so, but as a good shepheard seeing his lamb fallen into the mouth of the roring lion the Deuill, hasteth to help him, finding him out, vncouering his wounds, and pouring in the oyle of his mercy to heale his wounded soule. Seeing therefore that God makes such hast to call vs; let vs not be slow to answer, but with Samuell <hi>say; speake Lord for thy ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant heareth,</hi> let not Gods careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse be a cause of our carlesnesse,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18056:6"/>nor his watchfullnesse bringe vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a slumber, looke not to haue the sonne goe backe or stay still expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our repentance for <hi>the day pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth and the night commeth when no man can worke.</hi> The Greekes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire earthly wisdome, and the Iewes a signe, but <hi>we preach Christ crucified,</hi> &amp; woe to vs if that cannot conuert vs. I hope we looke not with <hi>Diues</hi> to <hi>haue one sent from the dead.</hi> If any such, I say not with A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham you haue Moses and the Prophets, but with the Apostle, <hi>in these last dayes God hath sent his sonne to call vs to repentance.</hi> Oh how long hath hee called vs to awake out of the sleep of sin, assuring vs if wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent our saluation is nearer then we thinke, if not our damnation nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer then wee feare. Wee read in the Canticles that our Sauiour standes knocking at his spouse dore while
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18056:7"/>the dew had bedewed his lockes; but she would not let him in: at length in her better cogitations she openeth the dore, and hee was gone: teaching vs that if we will not open the dore of our harts by the key of our repentance when hee knocks, the time shall come that wee shall seeke him, and hee will not be found.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lamen.</hi> 1.12</note> Harke harke what a lamentable complaint our Sauiour made on the crosse for the hardnes of our harts. <hi>Haue yee no regard all yee that passe by, behould and see if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you saw misery like my misery in the day of the visitation of the fearce wrath of God:</hi> as if he should say did you euer see such a woful spectacle, as one nailed hand and foote to the Crosse, his tender skul pierced with thornes, for the sinnes of others, as mine are? Yf you should see one iustly suffer such grieuous tortures,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18056:8"/>you cannot but pitty him, but if vniustly and yet patiently, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly for the loue he beareth to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, not his friends, but enemies; this would stay you in your grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test speede. Wherefore though you be in the full pursuite of your sinne, behould this my loue with the eye of faith as you passe by and it will mollifie your hardest harts. But if you will not regarde it, I call heauen and earth to witnesse against you: for at this my passion the stones claue in sunder on the earth, and the sonne lost his light in the heauens: wherefore your harts be more hard then stones, and sens<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse then the heauens, if you will not tremble and forsake your sinns. Thus doth Christ not with teares (as he called the Iewes) but with dropps of bloud seeke to mollifie our harts, least as wee came naked
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:18056:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:18056:8"/>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:18056:9"/>into the world so wee should re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne naked of the best riches. To day therefore if you will heare his voice harden not your harts to goe astray with the prodigall, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise your selues quick returne: do not with greeuing, quenching, and checking the good spirit lose him by degrees and thinke to finde him on the sudden, for, <hi>When Mary lost Christ but a dayes iourney she was three daies finding of him, and shall we lose him thirty or forty yeares,</hi> and thinke to finde him in the last houre of our death? shall wee be going from a city a whole yeare, or more, and think to returne in a moment? surely this were to delude our selues. Well therefore, saith the good father, hee that promiseth saluation to the repentant, hath not promised repentance when thou wilt: lest therefore the sinne of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18056:9"/>thy soule and the end of thy dayes make too neare a coniunction, and God leaue thee to thy selfe, so that thou depart with a burthen of sins vnrepented of; While it is to day heare his voice so louingly calling thee, for to morrow thou maist seeke it with teares, and not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine: to day, for this is the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table time, greiue not therefore the good spirit with <hi>cras,</hi> least your al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most come to nothing: to day re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, for it is more dangerous to sleepe with one sinne, then an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Scorpions; for they can but kil the body, this both body and soule and cast into hell fire. To day ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore heare his voice, least to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row hee say to you (as to his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples in an other sence) hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth sleepe and take your rest, for you shall be no more called for mee, and then good had it beene
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18056:10"/>for vs if we had neuer beene borne. Thus haue I (as loude as I could) sounded Gods trumpet in your eares, to awake you out of the dead sleepe of sinne, let him therefore that hath an eare, heare God cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vnto him <hi>where art thou.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Haec est vox interrogantis, incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pantis, et commiserantis</hi> first by way of interrogation: looke how a louing father dwelling in a wood inhabited with beasts, if he misse his sonne, searcheth euery pitt, calling with a shrill voice, fearing least some noughty beast hath deuoured him: by which voice his childe (who was fallen into a sleepe) is awaked; euen so (me thinkes) I see with the eye of faith God calling man who was fallen into a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous sleepe in the wildernes of sin, where the roring lyon was ready (if God had not preuented) to haue
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18056:10"/>deuoured him, but God in mercy cals to awake him out of the dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous sleepe of sinne. Was God ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant where man was? noe but man was ignorant where himselfe was, for he had sinned and knew not, but fled from God, and had runne hedlong into the pitt of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction <hi>(vndè non datur regres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus)</hi> had not God in mercy stayd him and cald him back; man was become a wilde tree therfore God the good husband-man commeth with the sword of his word to cutt off his topp gallant and graft in a sien <hi>scilicet,</hi> a knowledge of his fault, that so hee might repent.</p>
            <p>Secondlie, <hi>non tam interogantis quam increpantis vox est.</hi> It is by way of reprofe: for all Gods words before mans fall were commanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, and commendatory, <hi>appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bationis, non exprobationis,</hi> but
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18056:11"/>man sliding God fell to chiding as in this manner: where art thou, what hast thou done? who toulde thee thou wast naked? hast thou e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the forbidden fruit? euery word as a seuerall sword to pierce their naked harts. Thus you see beloued that it is a fearfull thing to fall into the hands of the liuing God: Iudge therefore your selues that you bee not iudged of the lord, for though our sinnes be superannate, worne out of date, yet if they be vnrepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of, God will call them to mind with a witnesse, and set them in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der against vs. There be foure sorts of men that get heauen, some by violence; such are they who suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer persecution for righteousnesse sake: others steale it (which is a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theft) when by our praiers and almes done in secret, we show a liuely faith which is rewarded o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18056:11"/>others purchase heauen, such are they who make them friends of their vnrighteous Mammon wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they shall be receiued into euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting habitation; the last sort are they which are drawne by threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings or punishments, and this is the worst way: for looke how the racke is to the body, to extort and wring a confession out of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender, so is punishment to the soule of the sinner; for a wounded conscience who can beare. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though God when he hath drawne the sword, doth not throw a way the scabbard, as if he would neuer put it vp againe: though hee will not alway be chiding, yet if wee sinne he will chastize vs with the chas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisements of men, hewing our harts and deuiding betweene the marrow and the bone, neuer ceasing to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish vntill he hath drawen vs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18056:12"/>and how much better it is to be drawne by gentle perswasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons then by the rod, iudge ye.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>non tam increpantis, quam commiserantis vox est,</hi> looke how a louing father pittying rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth and rebuking pittieth his son gone astray: so mee thinkes I see God rebuking man, in that hee would rather harken to the serpent his enemy, then to him his louing maker: but yet he pittieth him in that hee fell not like the Angells of malicious wickednesse, but of weaknesse. God had adorned man with all the heroicke vertues of the minde as iustice and mercy and such like, but man hauing sinned, they flew from him as not deigning to liue in so foule a cage, but flew backe to heauen, from whence they came, the one pleading for, and the other against man, iustice calling to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18056:12"/>God for reuenge, that seeing man had sinned against an infinite God and that with an infinite wil (as you may easily perceiue in his flying from God and that he was so farre from confessing his sinne, that he iustified himselfe, and accused God to his face as the author of his sinne in giuing him the woman) seeing therefore he had sinned soe with an infinite will, he pleads against man, that according to his offence hee might infinitely be punished: but mercy pleads for man, that seeing he hath sinned of weaknesse, God would be pleased not to take his mercy cleane from him, but in iudgement to remember mercy wherby he might call him to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and say peace to his soule. Thus God being solicited with sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry aduocates for and against man, hee calls to man to see what hee
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18056:13"/>could say for himselfe, that at least he might confesse against himselfe, and his iniquity might be forgiuen. Thus wee see <hi>abyssus abyssum inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat,</hi> the depth of our misery cald on the depth of Gods mercy, and the depth of his mercy cald on his wisdome &amp; power: &amp; so in mercy wisdome &amp; power he hath wrought our redemption. Wee read of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> when he heard of the death of his son <hi>Absolon</hi> that he dyed in his sin, he bewailed him, saying, <hi>O Abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, Absolon, O my sonne Absolon, would God I had died for thee my sonne, my sonne;</hi> here was a louing wish of a feeble father, but here (me thinkes) I heare a more louing and powerfull call: O <hi>Adam, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> O my sonne <hi>Adam,</hi> thou shalt not dye (if thou wilt repent) but liue, for I will dye for thee my son, my sonne, for though thy sinnes
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18056:13"/>make me to be spitted vppon, I will kisse thee with the kisses of my mouth; though my head be crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with thornes, I will crowne thee with glorie; though my side be thrust thorow with a speare, yet will I show thee the loue I beare thee at my heart; and albeit thy sinnes crucifie mee to the death, yet if thou wilt repent, I will procure thee life. O heare this (yee sonnes of <hi>Adam</hi>) to reuiue your dying and languishing spirits, for though God be iustly displeased with our offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, his anger endureth but the twinckling of an eye, but his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie for euer to them that repent; hee is a iust God, and punisheth to the third and fourth generation, them that with a stiffe necke in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and malice go on in sinning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him; but hee is a mercifull God, that shewes mercie to thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18056:14"/>in them that loue him, and endeauour to keepe his commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements. O turne you, turne you, why will you die? turne vnto God in sorrow, and contrition, that hee may turne vnto you in pittie and compassion, and heale your woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded consciences. This briefely of these words as they haue relation to God the maker of this inquisiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wherein he discouereth his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to sinne, and his compassion to the sinners, in that they had sinned of weakenesse: now this inquisiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is to bee considered as it hath relation to our estate which is fiue fould.</p>
            <p>First, <hi>vbi Paradisi,</hi> secondly <hi>vbi tenebrarum,</hi> thirdly, <hi>vbi miseriae,</hi> fourthly, <hi>vbi foliorum,</hi> fiftly, <hi>vbi gratiae.</hi> First, <hi>vbi Paradisi,</hi> what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state art thou in in Paradice? In the creation God who delighted to see
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18056:14"/>all his creatures good, ioyed to see man happie, hee spake the word, and they were created, but to make man, hee seemes himselfe for to commaund, and cals a consultation that nothing might bee wanting to the perfecting so excellent a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; he made him natures beauty, the forme of the creation, earths sole potentate, he infuseth a deuine Soule into a maiesticall body: and euerie soyle was not fit for man to dwell in, but hee must haue a Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, a place of pleasure, where the trembling trees bowed themselues in obedience, offering their fruites vnto him, the siluer streames ranne by, offering their continual seruice, and the maiesticall Lyon, with all other beastes subiected themselues more willingly than to <hi>Noah</hi> in the Arke. <hi>O foelix, O nimium foelix, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na si sua nosset, sed hinc illae lachrymae,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:18056:15"/>Man knew not when he was happy enough, it was not enough for him to bee Gods Vicegerent here on earth, but he seekes to be a God in knowledge: thus hee that desired to be more than a man, became a worme, and no man, in respect of that he was before; for he rebelling against God, all the creatures rebeld against him; the waters were ready to ouerwhelme him, as they did the <hi>whole World in the time of Noah;</hi> fire was readie to come downe from heauen, <hi>as to Sodome and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morra;</hi> the earth ready to swallow them, <hi>as Corath, Dathan, and Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram;</hi> beasts ready to deuoure them, as they did the children <hi>which mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Elisha;</hi> and the ayre readie to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect them with pestilence as in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids</hi> time. Thus man being in this great daunger in the midst of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse, God calls vnto man,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18056:15"/>
               <hi>Where art thou?</hi> as if he should say, how was it possible that thou shouldst forget so soone him, that was so carefull of thy wel-fare? what blessing was there with which (through my fatherly affection) I did not endow thee; for as if too little to make the world for thee, I made thee sole Gouernour vnder mee, and set thee vpon a Throne farre excelling <hi>Salomons</hi> in glorie, from which (by ingratitude) thou hast cast downe thy selfe; so that albeit I neede not aske who was I, that thou wert so vnmindefull of me, (for thy conscience tells thee) yet I cannot but cry, what was man that I was so mindefull of him, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he so little regarded? surely, I begin to repent that euer I made thee, for by sinne thou hast disfran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chized thy selfe of so ample amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, and thrust thy selfe into a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18056:16"/>dungeon. Beloued, if it were pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible for a people to enioy a para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice on earth, we doe heere in this land, for we haue that happy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth the Psalmist speaks of, <hi>Our wiues are like the vine, our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren like oliue branches round about our tables, our oxen strong to labour, our sheepe bring foorth thousands and ten thousands in our streets: and are not wee happy, that are in such a case, yea rather blessed in that wee haue the Lord for our God:</hi> For had not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Moseses</hi> beene instant in prayers for vs, we had perished (like the Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites) with quailesin our mouths, so greeuously doe wee daily abuse the blessings of God. It is not long since the plague swept away whole housholds in our land, great inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations by water, and the earth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied her increase; so that many poore soules, hauing their children
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18056:16"/>hanging on their tender brests, had nothing but salt teares to releeue them. But (may some say) what is this to vs? Surely, a warning to teach, that vnlesse wee repent, wee shall all likewise perish, and bee brought from our greatest plenty to that want, that wee shall desire a cup of colde water to coole our tongues, and we shall not obtain it.</p>
            <p>As this land is a modell of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, so many (like <hi>Adam</hi>) are rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed out of the dust, to be Gods vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth, like <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Dauid, from the sheephooke to the Scepter:</hi> or, as <hi>Saul, from seeking his fathers asses:</hi> or, like the Disciples, <hi>of fisher-men made fishers of men:</hi> I speake not this, as if all were raised out of the dunghill: for I know many are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly descended, yet it was God which raised their ancestours, and who likewise hath furnished them
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18056:17"/>with girts which are not hereditary: Therfore <hi>Plato</hi> sayd well, that God mingled the complections of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with gold, of their helpers with siluer, and the Commons with brasse: shewing that God furnisheth men with gifts fitting for their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: and therfore to shew all foule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouthed Papists, (who raile against the supremacy of our King) that God hath giuen him power Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticall as temporall, hee is so fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished with knowledge of Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that many Priests, both of the Papists and Protestants, who haue beene Proficients in serious studies, may notwithstanding learne of him. Seeing therefore that God thus bestoweth his gifts, that wee haue nothing that wee haue not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, let them that are exalted beware of pride, for if <hi>foelicitas su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbiae, superbia infoelicitatis sit parens:</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:18056:17"/>for <hi>superbus in solio est simia in te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto,</hi> in a fit place to breake his neck: and pride is the root of all euill, but <hi>vita ima,</hi> and <hi>sedes prima</hi> agree not; but <hi>verbum sapientibus satis est.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>vbi tenebrarum?</hi> in what estate of darknesse art thou? God made the Sunne to shine by day, and the Moone by night, and gaue his word to bee a light to their feet, and a lanthorne to their paths: but this is our condemnation, that wee loued darknesse better then light, and so gropt at noone-day, changing the estate of righteousnes for the poluted garment of sinne: And well may sinne be called dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse: First, in regard of the author of it, the Prince of darknesse. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, in that it brings vs to the darknesse of ignorance heere, and (if God in mercy preuent not) to that more then Aegyptian darknesse
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18056:18"/>heereafter. Our first parents being falne into this estate, God calls vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, to bring them to a sight of their sinne, that so they might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, as if hee should thus expostu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late with them; Was my burthen so heauy, and the yoake I layd on you so vneasie, that you could not longer beare it, but so soone cast it off? I did not cumber you with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny commands, for at that time I needed not, you could enuy none, for none more happy then your selues, there were no virgins to ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uish, no widowes to defloore, or wiues to defile, no Churches to rob by sacriledge, or brethren to bee opprest with vsury: In fine, I gaue you but one command, <hi>scilicet,</hi> to forbeare the fruit of one tree, and was this command so greeuous? had you not both store of fruit, for necessity and delight? did I not in a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18056:18"/>manner make my selfe poore, to your store? see then how vngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thou art, and <hi>ingratum modo dixerim omnia,</hi> this fowle beast <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude</hi> hath made a breach for all other sinnes: First, Beloued; our bodies are not so subiect to disea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, as our soules to sinnes, pride is the soules tympany, enuy the worme that gnaweth at the heart, wrath a pleurisie which will not be appeased without bloud, lust is the soules feauour: nay, whereas the body hath respit from sicknesse, the soule none from sinne, and all sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses haue their symptomes: yet wee so ignorant of sinne, that who knowes how oft hee offends; yea, many are so filthie, that you may trace them as a fox by his sent, yet they haue no feeling, <hi>oderunt pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re boni virtutis amore,</hi> as <hi>Seneca</hi> would not sinne, lest he should de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18056:19"/>so noble substance as the soule. And I read of <hi>Anselmus,</hi> that hee was wont to say, that if hee should see all punishments without sinne on one hand, and sinne without pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishments on the other, hee would imbrace punishments, and forsake sinne: Surely, it was a most Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian-like resolution; for what wise man hauing a many Iewells in the raine, would not couer them with his cloake (though he be well dren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with the raine, or beaten with haile himselfe) to keepe them from rusting: and doe wee not see that sin is as a putrified flie to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious oyntment, or as rust and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker to the soule? for if thy soule be adorned with vertue, as great ones with iewels, one foule sinne raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, takes away the lustre &amp; beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of them. How many men see we daily of good aspects, excellent
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18056:19"/>gifts, and comely personages, who by pride, selfe-conceiptednesse, drunkennesse, or such like vice, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow and staine all their other gifts, thus hatefull is sinne of it selfe: But Sinne and Punishments are twinnes, Sinne as the elder may feast it selfe within, but Punishment lieth at the doore, Idlenesse atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the Scuruy, Drunkennesse with the Dropsie, Pride with Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy, and our first Parents affected knowledge with our ignorance, which how great a punishment it is, I appeale to any ingenious na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: who cannot, but to his end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse greefe finde, that when he hath turned strength into weaknes, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row into drinesse, and his colour into palenesse, by watchings and continued studies, at length hee at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth <hi>hoc vnum scire,</hi> that he seeth no more then a prisoner at a creuice
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18056:20"/>in a dungeon, <hi>scilicet,</hi> that there is a Sunne which once enlightned him, which though hee cannot now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy, yet hee hopeth one day againe to be comforted with the cleere shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning beames thereof. But whither doth mine ignorance lead mee? I had almost forgot that the punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of sinne was reserued for the next place: but seeing that I am en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into this subiect, I hope I shall not digresse in touching this part, so farre as it expresseth the miserable estate of sinne: examine therefore, and you shall see what a sympathy there is betweene the punishment of God appoynted for sinne, and the estate of sinne: For first, the earth (for sin) brings forth thornes, briers, and thistles; so our hearts being become earthly, bring forth the briers of sin, and not the whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some fruit of righteousnesse, as you
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:18056:20"/>may see in children and fooles, who will sooner learne to cry bald-pate, then to sing <hi>Hosanna;</hi> and well may sinne bee compared to thornes, in that it hath the same power to teare the conscience, as the other doth the garment. Secondly, as for sin, in sweat wee eat our bread; so in sweat we eat the stolne waters and bread of iniquity. Doth not the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious man more vex his wretched soule at the prosperity of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous; then hee doth his righteous soule, at the sinnes of the wicked? Doth not the wrathfull man take more paines to execute his fury, then the patient man to put vp an iniury? I read of one, that being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous to goe to Olympus, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing discouraged with the tediousnes of the iourney, hee was counselled by his friend, to goe so farre euery day that way, as hee vsed to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18056:21"/>walke for his recreation, and at last he should ariue at his iournies end: So, if there be any (as I feare there be many) that would willingly goe to heauen, but that they see <hi>a Lyon in the way, and a Lyonesse in the path;</hi> I assure you (that if you would as much fight against and greeue your spirituall aduersaries, as you doe the good spirit of God, which sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth your redemption) you should at last ariue at the hauen of blisse: for so painefull are the wayes of wickednesse, that that is most true of the sinner, which is sayd of the woman, that in sorrow hee shall bring forth: Thirdly, as the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man shall haue a desire to her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and hee shall haue the rule of her: euen so wee, to bee wedded to our fleshly bodies (for skin for skin and all that a man hath, he will giue for his life) yet hath our flesh rule
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:18056:21"/>ouer vs, so that <hi>Paul</hi> himselfe could not but confesse, that <hi>hee had a law in his members, contrary to the law of God;</hi> For our spirits are like to a bird tied to a mill-stone, they may houer vp in heauenly cogitations; but soone againe are pulled downe with the masse of our fleshly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, as you may see in <hi>Peter, who was ready in spirit with his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster to die, but presently hee did him fearefully denie:</hi> In a word, our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt nature is so filled with the worme-wood and gall of the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternesse of sinne, that <hi>Nitimur in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tita cupimus{que} negata,</hi> the very for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding of an euill is enough to make vs desire it; yea, with the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, we sucke out poyson from the best flowers; from learning we ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pride; from courage, rashnes; from liberality, prodigality; yea, so are we naturally delighted in sin,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18056:22"/>that we delight to see others sinne: not vnlike him, that standing on the shoare, or rather being tossed with the waues at sea, should delight to see another drowned before his eyes: for
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Solamen miseris socios habuisse doloris</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sed miserum,</hi>—</l>
               </q> Like to him that ioyes to see his neighbours house fired, whereas he hath more cause to weepe, fearing that his will be the next. If this will not suffice to conuince thee from corruption, from thine own mouth I will condemne thee; for why hast thou consented with the body of this land, to make so many necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry penall statutes? it were cynicall to thinke to this end they were made, that great theeues might hang little ones; and it is the common folly, to compare them to spiders webs, wherin little flies are intangled, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18056:22"/>great ones breake thorow: for daily experience confuteth this errour. But if thou wilt looke into thine owne bosome, thou should soone finde out the cause, <hi>scilicet,</hi> thy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural corruption, for we are all natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally Atheists, ready to sin against God, the state, and nature. Hence proceede these heauen-threatning blasphemies, Church-deuouring sacriledges, vnmercifull extorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and such like sinnes flowing from a corrupt fountaine: for though with <hi>Hazael,</hi> we thinke we could not commit such euills, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse we were doggs; yet so dogged we are, that wee make no bones of them.</p>
            <p>Hence let vs learne,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vse. </seg>
               </label> not to delight in the falls of our brethren, but to pity them, saying with that good Father, <hi>Ille hodiè, ego cras,</hi> hee hath falne to day, I may fall to morrow.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18056:23"/>Secondly, let him that standeth, take heede hee fall not, for you see wee stand on slippery places: see how <hi>Esau</hi> hated <hi>Iacob,</hi> for getting from him his birth-right, how much more should wee hate sinne, which impouerisht all our ancestours. Thirdly, if at any time we doe sin, let vs comfort our selues in this, that <hi>wee haue an aduocate to the Father, Christ Iesus the righteous, hee is the propitiation for all our sinnes,</hi> for as the high Priest presented the names of the twelue Tribes on his brest-plate, so Christ the names of his Elect. So that, albeit with <hi>Ioseph,</hi> our garments bee rent by the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of our Mistresse and <hi>Dalilah,</hi> our flesh; and our body also cast af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the dungeon of the graue, yet (at last) shal we be brought forth to a Kingdom most glorious. Sweet Iesus bee to vs a Iesus, let thy pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18056:23"/>answer for our wrath; let thy mercy, for our vncharitablenesse; and thy righteousnesse, for our sin.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>vbi miseriae?</hi> what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state of misery art in? as if he should say, hast thou so soone forgot that I forbad thee the eating of the tree of knowledge, <hi>sub poena,</hi> which (like the Law of the Medes &amp; Persians) cannot bee reuoked. O miserable man, euill is thy estate, and better had it beene thou hadst neuer been, if thou wilt not now hearken vnto me, for in iudgement I will remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber mercy, and <hi>the seede of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man shall bruize the Serpents head:</hi> whereby, if thou wilt repent, thou shalt bee freed from the second death. See therfore thine own mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, &amp; by these symptomes and sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of the other, learne to shun that great and intolerable paine; for hauing eaten the stolne bread of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:18056:24"/>sinne, thou must now haue sower sawce. The Poets doe faine of <hi>Prometheus,</hi> that hee stole fire from heauen, whence <hi>noua febrium terris incubuit cohors:</hi> By <hi>Prometheus</hi> is meant <hi>Adam,</hi> by fire his affected knowledge, for as fire enlightneth, heateth, and kindleth, so his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge enlightned him to see his nakednesse, heated him, that hee blushed for shame, and kindled Gods wrath against him: So that (like vnmercifull fire) in a moment it brought them from the height of happines to the extreamest misery. I may compare vs sinners to <hi>Iob,</hi> who was not onely tormented with botches, but his friends were mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable comforters, and euery mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senger brought tydings of woe: this is our estate, our soules and bodies are defiled with the leprosie of sin, our breath stincks with the surphur
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18056:24"/>therof, our eares are deafe in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Gods word, our eyes bleared with ignorance, and our mouthes dumb to speake of Gods praise: Thus wee hauing metamorphosed our selues, we haue made God, of a louing father, an angry Iudge, our owne conscience mustreth vp ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusing thoughts to torment vs, and the best comforts that are sent vnto vs, are mixt with sorrow: so that I may well compare vs sinners to a Traytour, who while he is plotting mischeefe against the state, hath his weapons taken from him by one, and arrested by another, and cast in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a dungeon, and by his own guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines being condemned, euery day expects the executioner: So wee, while either plotting the hurt of our brother, or how to sinne against our God, if wee would but looke vpon our selues, might see that our
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:18056:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:18056:25"/>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:18056:26"/>weapons are taken away: for wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as God hath giuen to other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, weapons to defend and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose; as to the Horse, the hoofe; the Bull, the horne; the Boare, a tuske; and the Lyon, the paw; man onely is naked, and yet he will not forbeare to plot mischeefe, which while hee is brewing, perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture a bryer catcheth holde of him, and teares him, as if content with nought but his bloud, and if they had tongues to speake, they would say, that God (in wrath) hath sent them armed with so many prickes, as sundry bills and staues, to arrest vs of treason, for sinning against God. But alas, our affected knowledge hath cast such a mist of ignorance before our eyes, that wee cannot see our misery, like foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish prisoners that know the Iudge is at hand, the witnesses ready, the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:18056:26"/>bill of inditement drawne, the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner appoynted, and the place of torment certaine, yet doe they arme themselues to outface their misery: So we haue God our Iudge at hand, our consciences a hundred witnesses, the Diuell ready to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and all records sundry bills of indictment, to shew that we are vnthankfull to God, murtherers of our neighbours, enemies to our owne soules, and iniurious to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: So that <hi>Imminet mors, iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, infernus, &amp; omnia horrenda, &amp; quasi nihil ad nos, ridemus, ludimus, peccata peccatis adi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cimus.</hi> But as they when death approacheth, quake and tremble: so doe wee, <hi>O mors, quàm amara memoria tua ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini habenti solatium in hac vita?</hi> O death, how bitter is the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of thee to a man whose comfort depends on this life? For
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:18056:27"/>though thy estate is not like the Marchants, which hangs by cables, or rather in regard of his manifold dangers, by a twined thred; nor like the Vsurers, which is sure so long as the common Law lasts, if the deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour prooue not Bankrupt: but suppose thou wert like the rich man in the Gospell, that thou hadst not little but much goods, and that in possession, which is eleuen poynts of the Law, thou hast got it thou carest not how, and thou wilt bee sure to keepe it, let others haue wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try eyes for wanting of it, yet thou wilt laugh in enioying of it, and so thou mayst haue goods, thou ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest not for God: Imagin thou wert thus like the rich man, and wentst on as comically, what good would these goods doe thee, seeing thou must end tragically? for though he had gathered his crop, enlarged his
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:18056:27"/>barnes, sung a <hi>Requiem</hi> to his soule, yet had he a turbulent catastrophe, hearing this dolefull ditty; <hi>O foole, this night shall thy soule be taken from thee:</hi> Thus you see our wisdome is but foolishnesse with God, for God walks opposite to the greatest man, if a great sinner. Thus am I brought into the large sea of misery: but if I should search into euery creeke and arme thereof, my life would not suffice, I will onely carry you from the land of security, and point vnto you the principall creeks, that so you might bee sea-sicke, and bee the more healthfull euer after: but seeing teares are the best Oratours to expresse misery; while you saile along, bewaile your sinnes, which are the cause of this your mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serie in all ages and estates. As in our infancy wee come crawling into the world, and had wee so
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:18056:28"/>much vnderstanding to see it, wee might perceiue our mothers halfe dead by giuing vs life, and had wee not the help of others, the houre of our birth would end our life; in our youth correction (which is as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary as food) is a burthen and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable yoake: after, like vntamed heifers subiect to disordered passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; in olde age loathsome to our selues and others: <hi>these are the dayes wherein there is no pleasure,</hi> and as all ages, so all estates miserable; if rich, full of care, feare, and greefe; if of meane estate, subiect to discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; and if poore, God help; for thou canst looke for little of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifull man. Besides, the raw humours of the forbidden fruit are so vndigested, that notwithstanding all the help of nature and art, there are sundry diseases, which like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to furies, destroy vs, before wee
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:18056:28"/>can finde a remedy, some gnaw at the throat, others dart at the heart, others weigh downe the kidneyes, and racke the whole body: How many haue lost their liues with fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching in of Indian druggs? And o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in searching out of the vertue of them? And notwithstanding their care and paine, we get that in a moment, which cannot be clawd off in our liues. Besides these dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases, all the creatures conspire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst vs, for like to <hi>Acteons</hi> doggs, seeing vs metamorphosed, they fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously pursue vs, &amp; as if this were not miserie enough, wee wadge warre one against another, so that man who was created a milde and louing creature is by sinne become <hi>lupus, imò daemon,</hi> for there is not the like disparitie betweene any creatures of the same <hi>species,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene man and man, as you may
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:18056:29"/>see by our artilleries, roaring can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, swords, guns, and pistolls; for notwithstanding God hath blest our land with a peaceable King, that delights not in shedding of bloud; yet twenty thousand pounds yeerely doth not suffice to streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then our land against our enemies; and, as if it were not misery enough to haue enemies abroad, wee are enemies to our selues, our flesh figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting against the spirit, and which is more strange, our flesh fighting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it selfe: witnesse those iarres at bed, and discontents at boord, between man and wife: And, which is so vnnaturall a thing, as you shall not finde it amongst the bruitish beasts: many men lay violent hands vpon themselues, like bad tenants, so farre from paying of their rent, that they pull downe their Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lords houses, and as to the body,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:18056:29"/>so are not miseries wanting to the soule, as sundry passions; for by choler we attempt that which after destroyes vs, or brings perpetuall repentance: melancholy affrights vs sleeping, and torments vs wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king; mirth incenseth vs to lust; loue is accompanied with iealousie, hope with feare, and our ioy ends in sorrow, teaching vs that our hearts being made for God alone, no earthly thing can content them, while they returne to God, from whom by sin they are gone astray. The Israelites before they came to the wildernesse of Sine, tasted of the bitter waters, lest they should be delighted in building of taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles there, and hinder their iourney to the promised land: so wee much more (while wee walke in this wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernesse of sinne) must eat with sweat, lest we neglect the manna for
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:18056:30"/>our soules. To this end wee haue sundry afflictions, as so many little deaths to fit vs for eternall life: If yee therefore seeke happinesse, yee doe well; for thereunto yee are created: but ye must seeke it where it is to bee found, for <hi>resurrexit non est hic,</hi> heere in the midst of life you are in death; heere you must suffer with Christ, that after you may raigne with him; heere beare the crosse, that after yee may sit on the throne: thus like wise mariners, if wee sit at the end of the ship, wee may guide it to the hauen of blisse. Let vs therefore with the Doue, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a long time houered, &amp; found no rest in this deluge, let vs (I say) returne to the Arke of the Church, where wee may haue rest for our soules, following this example wee haue before our eyes, which (mee thinkes) is a fit Commentary vpon
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:18056:30"/>this Text, as wee may see by expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stulating with this our sister, before wee take our last farewell of her: First, wert thou not happily descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the same root, from whence sprung that honourable Branch, to whom the whole land shall stand for euer obliged, for his painefull and profitable expositions of our common lawes? hath not God blest thee with three husbands, by one of the which thou hadst issue, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Mingy</hi> Counsellor of the Law, in whom thou liuest now, being dead? and now in thine olde age (though thou bee silent) the parish where thou didst liue will witnesse that thou hadst no churlish <hi>Nabal:</hi> But what meanes this still silence? Hearke, hearke, me thinkes I heare her say, <hi>Fui quod es, er is quod sum,</hi> I haue beene as able to speake as you, but now death hath sealed vp
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:18056:31"/>my lips, but this is my comfort, that I did die daily, and as I often read of the Martyrs, so I goe reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to my graue, <hi>Non enim Deus deseruit,</hi> but hath made death a bridge for mee to passe ouer to a better life. Let vs therefore bewaile our owne misery in losing of her, for this congregation hath lost a principall member to accompany at prayer, hearing the Word and receiuing the Sacraments, the poore (which are many) hath lost money for their purses, meat for their bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, &amp; cloths for their backs: &amp; I my selfe, all the encouragement I had in this place in the worke of my mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry: but whom wee haue lost, I am assured that the heauens haue found, and wee by following her good examples, may goe to her, she cannot come to vs.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>vbi foliorum?</hi> what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:18056:31"/>art thou vnder the figg-leaues. You may read of a widow, which desiring to see better, had her eyes closed vp by a cunning Physician, who then stole away her treasure, which her eyes being open missing, complained that shee saw worse then euer: This was the estate of our first parents, for they had made a proposition, that it was better to hearken to Sathan, then God; that so they might see better, whereas indeede they saw themselues in a worse estate, and therefore sought to the figg-leaues for couers: God therefore seeing the euill euent makes an <hi>Assumpsit,</hi> by questioning with them, that so they might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude against themselues, that they were auerted, and therefore might labour to be conuerted, as if in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect hee should thus say, Alas silly man, who hath blinded thee, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:18056:32"/>bewitched thee, that thou thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kest to couer thy nakednesse by fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaues from my all-seeing eye? or whither fliest thou so fast from me, who am thy shield, thy buckler, thy defence, thy shepheard, thy God, thy father? O whither canst thou flie from my presence, <hi>If thou clim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>best to the heauens, there is my throne; if thou takest the wings of the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and fliest to the further most part of the earth, there is my foot-stoole; if thou diuest into the depth of the sea, there is my power; or if thou runnest headlong into hell, there shall I meet thee with my iudgement:</hi> So that if thou wouldst flie, thou couldst not; or if thou wert able to flie, it would not help thee, <hi>O hide not thy sinne, for in this thou canst not prosper; but acknowledge it, so shalt thou haue mercy, for with mee is plenteous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</hi> Beloued, wee haue all
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:18056:32"/>sinned with our first parents, none but Christ the immaculate Lamb can say, <hi>Who can rebuke me of sinne? Let vs therefore acknowledge our sinnes, and God is faithfull and iust to forgiue them,</hi> as if hee sayd, if thou hide thy sinnes God is faithful to punish them; but if thou confesse them, hee will forgiue them. O yee that are in the same estate of iniquity, beware of hiding your sinnes, which is done two wayes: First, by extenuating them: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, by couering of them. 1. By extenuating, esteeming of drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, as good fellowship; and wantonnesse, but a tricke of youth; and pride, cleanlinesse; couetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, good husbandry; ignorance, innocency; giddinesse, zeale; fury, manhood; oppression, the making of the most of ones owne; and vsu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, a lawfull gaine: Thus Sathan
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:18056:33"/>takes on him the shape of an Angell of light, and lest sinne should ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in his likenesse, he cloths this fox in a sheeps skin. And so setting such a varnish on sinne, that it see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth so pleasing, that wee can bee content to be trumpets of our own shame, with <hi>Absolon committing fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinesse in the sight of the Sunne.</hi> Secondly, wee hide sinne by coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of it: First, by attributing it to the euilnesse of the times: Such are like to <hi>Harpastes</hi> a blinde woman, who would not beleeue shee was blinde, but that all places were darke; so they, that the world is bad, and all are sinners, as they are: whereas, as much difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the sinnes of others and theirs, as betweene light and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; for the righteous cannot sin with that full consent, delight, and continuall practise, as they doe.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:18056:33"/>Others say of sin, as <hi>Peter</hi> of Christ, <hi>non noui,</hi> for indeede they are as free from it, as the sea of water: others with <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Iuda</hi> can condemne sinne in their deerest friends, but not in themselues: others (like <hi>Thamar</hi>) muffle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, as if none saw them; or with <hi>Gehezi,</hi> say they walk not the paths of iniquity: but the spirit of the Lord is present euery where, vnco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering and disclosing the secrets of of all hearts: to this end hath hee placed the conscience in the midst of the soule, as the Iudge of our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and hath giuen it a voyce to pursue vs, that therein God may bee iustified. I deny not but that there are sleeping and cauterized consciences which are seared, but they shall bee awaked: and (like a dogge) they will flie at the throat, and we shall say vnto them, as <hi>Ahab</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:18056:34"/>to the Prophet, <hi>Hast thou found me, ô mine enemy? agree therefore with this aduersary in the way,</hi> for why should our tongues be loth to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse that which our faces and other members acknowledge? For if thou beest accused of that particular euill thou neuer didst commit, the bloud comes into thy face, acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging thou hast the root of sinne, and so wedded vnto it, that there is no euill so great, but thou art prone to commit: and if any euill befall vs, wee strike our brests, as if there lay the cause, and if the punishment be great, wee teare our haire and mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sacre our flesh, as if wee would bee reuenged of our selues. Thus nature forceth vs to confesse in action, and shall not the word of God wring out a confession from our hearts? I haue read a fable which I will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert, to commend vnto you the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:18056:34"/>morall: the fable is, That one being at confession, the Diuell intruded himselfe, and being asked to what end he came; he answered, to make restitution. (I wish Vsurers, Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners, Church-robbers, and such like, would learne of their beloued Schoole-master this lesson) But what would hee restore? Shame, which hauing before stolne away, to make him shamelesse in sinning, hee had now brought againe, to make him ashamed to confesse. O let not Sathan so delude, let vs bee ashamed to sinne, in that God hath forbidden it; but not to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our sins, for God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded it.</p>
            <p>To conclude, the first degree of righteousnesse is, not to sinne; the second, to acknowledge and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake our sinnes: wherefore, as by telling our dreame, it is a sure signe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:18056:35"/>wee are awaked: So a sorrowfull confession, that we are awaked out of the sleepe of sinne: Seeing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the night is past, let vs (by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession) assure our consciences, that wee haue put away the deedes of darknesse; which mercy God grant to euery one.</p>
            <p>Lastly, <hi>vbi gratiae;</hi> see what need thou hast of grace; for euill is thy estate, and requires mercy, yet is not thy cause so bad, that thou shouldest despaire; for as in thee there is store of iniquity, so in mee there is much mercy, thy sinnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a fit obiect for declaration of my mercy; for I will send my Son, the seede of the woman, to bruize the Serpents head.
<note place="margin">1 Kin. 6.</note> When the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets seruants helfe of iron was falne into the water, <hi>Elizeus</hi> tooke a peece of wood, and threw it in, and caused the iron to swim aboue
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:18056:35"/>water, so that his man restored it to the owner, we are like iron, hardned in our sinnes; but Christ (by the power of his death on the crosse) hath raised vs from the whirlepoole of destruction, and holds vs vp by his grace, that after we haue swum a while in this sea of misery, wee may render our soules into the hands of God our right owner. Thus mercy hath life (as I may say) by our death in sinne, sinne being precedent in vs,
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> the act of mercy followes after, for by sinne came grace,
<note place="margin">2 Esdr. 8.31.36.</note> and because of sinners God shall be called mercifull; for in this Gods goodnesse shall bee praised, in that hee is mercifull to vs, who haue not the substance of good workes;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>August. in Psal.</hi> 32.</note> for the heauens needed not Gods mercy, because in them there is no misery: but the earth needed it, in that it is poluted with
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:18056:36"/>mans sinne, and how much more doth our estate require it, who are a lump of sinne? but where the sin of man abounded, there Gods mercy much more abounded; for all things worke for the best to them which loue God, <hi>Etiam peccata Domine</hi> (as <hi>Augustine</hi> sweetly) for by sinne wee see our infirmities, which brings humility; for thereby wee are exalted to perfect rest and endlesse peace. Thus by grace are wee saued; for without it wee are wholly deficient, and that onely is sufficient for vs, both to mooue vs to serue God (for God hath sent his <hi>spirit to worke grace in our hearts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit.</note>
               <hi>tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching vs to deny all vngodlinesse and worldly lusts, to walke righteously and soberly in this present worldly</hi>) And likewise, that soly mooueth God to salue vs:
<note place="margin">Fulgentiu.</note> so that, <hi>Datur ex gratia non solùm iustificatis vita bona, sed glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficatis
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:18056:36"/>vita aeterna:</hi> The first you may see in <hi>Peter,</hi> who was <hi>vas gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae;</hi> for when, as by lamentable experience, hee had found that hee had not strength sufficient in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, to keepe him from denying his Lord, &amp; Master, but presuming that hee was strong enough to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter the whole world, he found himselfe too weake to withstand a silly Damosell, by this hee learnt wholly to deny himselfe and his owne strength; for being thrice asked after, If hee loued Christ, hee answered, thou knowest, as (if he should say) I haue no power, but that is giuen from thee, and how long it will bee continued, it is best knowen to thee, and thou no soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner takes this grace from me, but I fall from thee, so that in me there is neither strength nor knowledge of louing thee. O yee that boast so
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:18056:37"/>much of your succession from <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> if you bee his successours, make it knowen by doing his workes, <hi>sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet,</hi> by denying your owne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and establishing Gods grace; trust not to your owne strength, for (like a broken reede) it is already run into your flesh, as you may see (by your great polutions) which haue been in your holiest places; but rely wholly on Gods grace, for <hi>suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficit gratia,</hi> like the widowes oile, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting all the time of the famin, euen so long as we hunger &amp; thirst after righteousnesse, vntill wee shall bee satisfied in glory; for although such is our frailty, we are vnable to serue God, yet hath grace wrought a will in vs, and God for Christs sake ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts our wills and endeauours, supplyeth our spirituall wants, and pardoneth our defects, <hi>Omnia igi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur mandata adimplentur cum quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:18056:37"/>non fit ignoscitur:</hi> for our righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse consists of remission of sinnes, not perfection of vertues, that man onely being blessed, to <hi>whom the Lord imputeth no sinne, for if God entreth into iudgement, no flesh shall be iustified; all the righteousnes of man being as a stained cloth:</hi> So that our good works cannot be iustified before God for their worth: how far are those works then, from making satisfaction for our sins, which are not of God required, but fetched out of our owne braine (as hearing of masses, going on pilgrimage, wearing haire-cloth, making of vowes, whipping themselues, with such like, <hi>opera supererogationis,</hi> su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous workes, which God ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer commanded: and therefore are false coyne, deseruing death for minting it, and shall neuer be taken for payment of Gods all-seeing eye)
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:18056:38"/>for wee are dead in <hi>Adam,</hi> so that our best thoughts are meere mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheefe and malice against God,
<note place="margin">Gal. 2 10. 1 Cor. 8.46.</note> and when we haue done all we can, wee are vnprofitable seruants. All our imaginations &amp; thoughts are conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually euill,
<note place="margin">Gen. 6.5. Eph. 2 1. <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oh. 15.5. <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 3.</note> wee are dead in sinne, and can doe no good, no not thinke a good thought, so that <hi>Augustine</hi> saith well,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>August. d<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ra<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. cap.</hi> 8</note>
               <hi>Non libertate gratiam, sed gratia libertatem:</hi> &amp; <hi>Bernard, Natura volentes, gratia benè volentes,</hi> by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture wee may will, but it is grace whereby wee haue power to will good, a good thought is <hi>gratia infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sa,</hi> a good word <hi>gratia effusa,</hi> and a good act <hi>gratia diffusa.</hi> For with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith in Christ,
<note place="margin">Rom. 3.9. Luk. 17.10</note> it is impossible to please God, all which cannot be denied, vnlesse they deny the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as hereticall, and directly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their holy Church, deseruing to be burnt for heretickes, for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:18056:38"/>tradicting their Seruice and Masse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bookes: But (poore soules) rather then they will lose their whole in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest in <hi>Peter,</hi> they will imitate him in his infirmity, by trusting to their owne strength, and so like him, they with cursing &amp; banning, with bell, booke, and candle-sticke, deny their Lord and Sauiour, as scorning to be beholding to him, for his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse, as the Doctors of Louain teach,
<note place="margin">Concil. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. sect <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> can. de Ius<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <hi>That God may not impute righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse to any thorow faith, vnlesse he be righteous of himselfe:</hi> And the counsell of Trent hath concluded, <hi>That whosoeuer will defend,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conc. Trid<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> de <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ap. ca<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 10.</note>
               <hi>that the vngodly are iustified by faith only, and that for the obtaining of Gods mercy, workes are not needfull; let him bee accursed, and whosoeuer will maintain that all sinnes (after baptisme) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, should be forgiuen; or, at lest, may be forgiuen only thorow faith, and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:18056:39"/>power of baptism, let him be accursed;</hi> whereby you may perceiue that baptisme doth not purge &amp; cleanse the spouse,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>it. 3.5. <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 5.26.</note> that she might be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out spot or wrinckle (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth) For after baptisme wee haue a dangerous sea to swim tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, And therefore (say they) we must haue the tree of penance, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may swim as lustily (as with a paire of hoggs bladders) and this tree (they say) consists of three branches; shrift, contrition, and satisfaction; and therefore some of the Romish Champions haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omish <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e-hiue.</note> that Christ hath satisfied for original sin, <hi>scilicet,</hi> fed vs when we could not fly, but now our feathers are full-growen, wee must fly and helpe our selues: but the mother, the holy Church, stands more on her owne worth, and will not be in Gods debt, but wil cleere the score,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:18056:39"/>and that she may stop Gods mouth that hee shall haue no cause to say,
<note place="margin">The th<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of Sent<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, dist<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 20. in th<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> conclus<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that she is beholding to him for his grace, shee will satisfie in part for originall sinne, saying, <hi>Although the merits of Christ are the most speciall desert, thorow which Gods mercy, and the way vnto the Kingdome of heauen is granted vnto vs, yet this notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing is in no wise to bee reckoned, for the onely whole and full satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> And therefore for the satisfying for originall sinne, they adioyned the merits of the Sacrament of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme, which giue vnto men mercy, <hi>ex opere operato,</hi> and to say all in a word, that wee must satisfie for all sinnes, and stand in no neede of grace. For they magnifie our pure Naturals, as able to performe good workes congruously meritorious; saying, that <hi>Voluntas est absolutè &amp; simpliciter actiua:</hi> but thus doing,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:18056:40"/>they doe not imitate him, which threw away his cloake to goe to Christ; but the childe <hi>Samuel,</hi> who being called of God, ranne to <hi>Eli.</hi> But their manifold fals are suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to confute them, and there is no more to be sayd, but all are deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to God, and stand in neede both of supporting and directing grace; for heere wee are ignorant trauellers, and want a guide to vs, <hi>Nudos nos in fide prima gratia genuit, &amp; in assumptione nudos eadem salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>oh. 8.1.</note>
               <hi>I</hi> (saith Christ) <hi>am the light of the world, hee that followes mee shall not walke in darknesse, but shall haue the light of life:</hi> So that wee sitting in darknesse, hee comes like a good friend to enlighten vs;
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>oh. 8.51.47.</note>
               <hi>Verily, if any keepe my word, hee shall not see death.</hi> Now what is it to keepe his word, but to beleeue the word of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell? In a word, what is the whole
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:18056:40"/>word, but <hi>tuba gratiae,</hi> a trumpet of grace, sounding in our eares this sweet ditty; that, as by one <hi>Adam</hi> all die, so by Christ all are restored to life,
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.2.</note>
               <hi>O miserable man</hi> (saith <hi>Paul) who shall deliuer me from this body of death:</hi> Thankes be to God thorow Christ, as if he should say, why stand I staring on mine owne vnworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, seeing it is Christs merit, which must giue entrance vnto the presence of God, <hi>Qualecun{que} sit ergo peccatum,</hi> of what high nature soeuer therefore thy sinne bee (if thou wilt repent) God will pardon it.
<note place="margin">Esa. 65.7.</note> Beware therefore, that by desperation, thou shut not his hands, adde not this to thy former sinne, but forsake thy euill way, and returne vnto the Lord, and hee will haue mercy on thee, for hee is <hi>multus ad ignoscen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum,</hi> very ready to forgiue: com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort then thy selfe with this in thy
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:18056:41"/>strongest temptation, oppose a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Sathan Christ who is stron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; and against our weaknesse, his grace; against our sinne, his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse; against death, his resurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, who is the first fruits of the resurrection; and against hels torture, heauens glory: Let vs wholly distrust in our selues, and trust in him; for he is our Preist, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, Light, Sauiour, Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Propitiation, Oblation, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, Iustification, and Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication: O Lamb of God, that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kest away the sinnes of the world, haue mercy vpon vs; and so guide vs heere with thy grace, that wee may dwell with thee for euer in glory. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:18056:41"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>